感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
本剧改编自圣经  它们曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
《圣经》前情提要
Previously on the Bible...
起初
In the beginning...
天主创造天地
God created the heavens and the earth.
因为人类的败坏 上主决意毁灭世界
Then human failings led him to destroy his creation.
错误的选择  错误的决定
Wrong choices, wrong decisions.
诺厄之后，一个新的开始
After Noah, a new beginning...
而且天主给亚巴郎一个许诺
and a promise for Abraham.
天主同我说话了
God has spoken to me.
他将指引我们去新的家园
He will lead us to a new home.
他保证我的后裔会多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
但埃及人的奴役
But enslaved by Egypt,
让亚巴郎的后裔生活在水深火热之中
Abraham's descendants suffered
直到一名新的领袖出现
until a new leader emerged...
谁将成为以色列最伟大的英雄
who would become Israel's greatest hero.
-你是谁  -我是梅瑟
- Who are you? - My name is Moses.
天主派我回来
God has sent me
给你们自由
to set you free.
自由
Freedom?
他们能自由选择成为奴隶还是死人
They're free to choose slavery or death!
我这一生都被法郎奴役
All my life, I have been Pharaoh's.
我再也不会是奴隶了
I will never be a slave again.
若苏厄  天主与我们同在
Joshua, God is with us.
冲啊
Ride!
主啊
Lord!
跟我走
Follow me!
天主让我们摆脱了奴役
God has delivered us from slavery!
我们将在应许之地生活
We're giong to live in the promised land.
亚巴郎的梦想
Abraham's dream
是我们的未来
is our future.
现在你就是我们的未来  若苏厄
You are our future now, Joshua.
你必须攻下那块本属于亚巴郎的应许之地
You must take the land promised to Abraham.
梅瑟带领以色列人来到应许之地的边界
Moses has led the Israelites to the edge of the promised land.
在若苏厄的带领下  他们必将征服它
Under Joshua, they must conquer it.
圣经
四十年后
主啊
Lord.
梅瑟传下这十诫时  我和他在一起
I was with Moses when he handed down these commandments.
我见证了这份至圣盟约
I was witness to the covenant,
见证了赐予我们圣洁国度的承诺
the promise of a holy nation.
求你帮助我建立这个国度
Help me to forge that nation,
领导你的子民继承他们的土地
to lead your people to inherit their land.
若苏厄
Joshua!
上主将我们从埃及解救出来
The Lord brought us out from Egypt,
他承诺会将这块土地赐予我们
he promised us this land.
很快
And soon...
它就会是我们的了
it will be ours!
过来
Come!
你们准备好了吗
Are you ready?
我们会搜查整个城市
We'll search the whole city.
找一条能让我进去的路
Just find me a way in.
我们必须攻下耶利哥
We must take Jericho.
这是我们与盟约之地间唯一的障碍了
It's all that stands between us and the Promised Land.
白天才能取水
You can only collect water in daylight.
回家去  回去
Go home. Go. Go.
待在家里
Stay indoors.
以色列人随时可能进攻
The Israelites can attack at any time.
辣哈布  我的小妓女
Rahab, my little whore.
你在外头做什么
What are you doing out, hmm?
你知道外面不安全
You know it's not safe.
安全得很
Safe enough.
没人是安全的
No one is safe.
我会照顾好自己
I can look after myself.
回去吧
Go home.
你们在这儿做什么  以色列人
What are you men doing here? Israelites!
-快跑  -以色列人来了
- Go! Go! - Israelites!
以色列人
Israelites!
哥哥
Brother...
-为了以色列  -为了以色列
- For Israel! - For Israel.
快
Quick!
这边  再找点人手过来
Over here! Get more men!
我们得躲进去  小心
We've got to get inside. Look out.
决不能让他们跑了  挨家挨户搜
They must not escape. Go door to door.
进去
In here!
所有人  都回家去
Everyone, return to your homes!
人呢
Hello?
别作声  我保证不会伤害他
Keep quiet and I promise I won't hurt him.
你发誓
Swear?
是的
Yes...
-你们是以色列人  -你听说过我们吗
- You're Israelites. - You've heard about us?
你们有个能呼风唤雨  分开海水的神
You have a god who commands the winds and parts the seas.
他让我们摆脱奴役
He saved us from slavery.
我们是被他选中的子民
We are his chosen.
城里的人都忌惮你们
This whole city is terrified of you.
你们有如此神通广大的神
How can we fight a people
我们怎么可能打败你们
whose god can do that?
开门  开门
Open up! Open up!
-进去  -把门打开
- Back inside! - Open the door!
这条路能出去吗
Can we get out that way?
帮帮我们  我们也会帮你的
Help us, and we will help you.
走吧  我会尽力拖住他们
Go. I'll stall them if I can.
打开门
Open the door!
跟我们一起走吧
Come with us.
不行  我还有家人
I can't. My family...
当我们军队攻进来的时候
When our army comes,
把这个挂在你门上
hang this on your door,
这样他们就不会伤害你们
so they will know not to harm you.
你将免于这场灾祸
You'll be passed over.
待在这儿
Stay here.
若苏厄
Joshua!
告诉我  找到进城的方法了吗
Tell me, did you find a way in?
-有突破口吗  -城墙上没有
- Is there a weakness? - Not in the walls.
但百姓心中有
But in their hearts.
若苏厄  我们遇到一个女人
Joshua, we met a woman.
她认为这座城市已经是天主的了
She thinks God has taken the city already.
他们知道天主与我们同在
The people melt in fear
都陷入恐慌  不战自溃
because they know he is with us.
天主确实与我们同在
God is with us!
但我们仍要想办法进城
But we've still to find a way in.
梅瑟
Moses,
我的老朋友
my old friend,
你会怎么做
what would you do?
主啊  当我还是奴隶的时候
Lord, when I was a slave
你向我展现了你的慈爱与大能
you showed me your love and your power.
你给了我新的生命
You have given me new life.
现在你想让我们回头吗
Would you have us turn back?
你...你是谁
Who... who are you?
我祈祷你是帮助我们的
I pray you are with us
不是帮助我们敌人的
and not with our enemies.
我是天主派来的
I am with God.
上主军旅的元帅
Commander of the Lord's Army.
我主有什么话吩咐我们
What does he ask of us?
主为梅瑟把海水分开
The Lord parted the waters for Moses.
为你
For you...
主将使城墙塌陷
...he will split rock.
你必须这么做
This is what you must do...
你们所有的战士每天
March around the city once a day
要围绕这城转一遭
with all the armed men.
这样转六天
Do this for six days.
抬着约柜  里面有天主的诫命
Carry the Ark with you. It contains God's commandments,
他将与你们同在
and he is with you.
但第七天，要围绕城转七遭。
Then, on the seventh day, march around the city seven times.
然后司祭用羊角号吹起长声。
Then the priests should make a long blast with the ram's horn.
你们一听见角声
As soon as you hear the sound of the trumpet,
众百姓要大声呼喊
all the people shall shout a great shout.
他们来了
It's happening!
荣耀将会降临
Glory will come.
他的确是这世界的创造者
He truly is the shaper of the world.
我们要把这座城献给主
We give this city to the Lord!
耶利哥是我们的
Jericho is ours!
只有妓女辣哈布与她家中所有人的可以存活
Only Rahab the prostitute and her family may be spared,
这是天主的旨意
for God said she must be spared...
因为她帮助了我们
for the help she gave us.
天主兑现了他的承诺
God has kept his promise.
只要我们遵从主
If we obey Lord,
一切皆有可能
anything is possible!
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
若苏厄死后一百年
A hundred years after Joshua.
以色列十二个部落遍布应许之地
The twelve tribes of Israel have spread out across the promised land.
但他们四面楚歌
But hostile neighbors surround them.
培肋舍特人武器精良  训练有素
Better armed and better trained.
是以色列人最致命的威胁
The Philistines are the deadliest threat.
由于缺少梅瑟和若苏厄这样杰出领袖的领导
Without great leaders like Moses or Joshua to unite them,
以色列人必须倚仗被称为"民长"的本土英雄
the Israelites must rely on local heroes called Judges.
三松就是其中之一
People like Samson.
母亲  来
Mother, come.
这种日子什么时候才能到个头啊
When will this all stop?
我也不知道
I don't know.
你必须反抗
You must fight them.
那是天主希望你做的  三松
It's what God wants you to do, Samson.
那是天主创造你的原因
It's why God created you.
记住他的天使跟我说的话
Remember what his messenger told me.
别害怕
Don't be afraid.
你原是石女 从未生育 但是你要怀孕生子
Though you are barren, God will give you a son.
感谢您
Thank you.
不过仔细听好了  这是有条件的
But listen carefully, there are conditions.
你当谨记  清酒浓酒都不可喝
See to it that you drink no alcohol
各种不洁的东西也不可以吃。
and eat nothing unclean.
儿子出生后  他永远不可剃头
And when your son is born, his hair must never be cut.
这是他作为献于天主的人的标记
This will be the sign that the boy is a Nazarite.
他自出生起  便归天主
He is given to God, from his birth to his death.
他会从培肋舍特人手中解救以色列
He will begin to deliver Israel from the Philistines.
你的力量源自天主
Your strength comes from God.
你背负着赶走培肋舍特人的使命
Your duty is to drive the Philistines away.
三松非但没有对抗培肋舍特人
Instead of fighting the Philistines,
反而爱上了一个非利士女子  并娶她为妻
Samson falls in love and marries one.
-让我和她谈谈  -当然
- Let me talk to her. - Of course.
母亲  难道爱不是源自天主吗
Mother, does love not come from God?
您想让我怎么办
What would you have me do?
就因为我爱的这个女人是培肋舍特人
Reject the woman I fell in love with
我就要抛弃她吗
just because she's a Philistine?
你的爱能保护我们不被他们伤害吗
Will your love protect us from them?
三松  三松
Samson! Samson!
我们得给以色列人点颜色瞧瞧
We need to send these Israelites a message,
让他们明白
make it clear to them.
我们的女人不是他们可以染指的
They cannot take our women.
我们两族永远不能通婚
Our people should never mix.
要怎么抓住他
How are we going to get to him?
不用抓...他
We're not going to get to him.
开门
Open up!
-三松在哪儿  -我不知道
- Where is Samson? - I don't know.
-他在哪儿  -他不在这里
- Where is he? - He's not here.
父亲  父亲  不要
Father! Father! No!
父亲  不要  不要啊
Father! No! No!
-动手  -求你们了  不要这样
- Do it. - Please, no.
你是我们民族的耻辱
You are a disgrace to our people.
-求求你  -我求你  求你了
- Please... - Please, I beg you.
-求你  父亲  父亲  -别碰她
- Please... Father! My father! - Don't touch her!
父亲  不要
Father! No!
不  不要
No! No!
求求你  求你们了  别这样
Please... I'm begging you, no.
求你们了  不要啊
Please no!
为吾妻
For my wife!
培肋舍特人
Philistines.
-快来  -救救我们
- Over here! - Help us!
救命
Help us!
求求你  放了我们  放了我们
Please, free us! Free us!
抓住那个以色列人
Get the Israelite!
只有一个人能有这种能耐
One man did this.
他在哪儿  他的族人一定知道
Where is he? His people must know.
你
You!
你把三松找来见我
You will bring Samson to me.
越快越好
And you will do it quickly.
我一天不见到他
And for every day I do not see him,
就杀一个以色列人
one of you will die.
即刻生效
Starting now.
不  不  不要  求你了  别
No... No! No! Please, no!
三松
Samson?
Samson!
三松
Samson?
三松  你在吗
Samson? Are you there?
母亲
Mother?
我没想到您会来  请宽恕我
I wasn't expecting you. Forgive me.
我们是来劝说你的  三松
We have come to reason with you, Samson.
-劝说  -你必须停止杀缪
- Reason? - You must stop the killing.
求你了
Please.
你杀了那么多培肋舍特人
For every Philistine you kill,
现在有两个培肋舍特人来找我们报仇了
two more appear, seeking revenge.
我只是以其人之道还治其人之身
As they did to me, so I have done to them.
如今培肋舍特人是我们的统治者
The Philistines are our rulers now.
每个人都应该做他们认为正确的事
Everyone must do what they think is right.
不  三松
No, Samson.
你必须为你的族人  为天主
You must do what is right for your people.
做正确的事
For God.
而不是为你自己
Not for yourself.
你必须牺牲自己  三松
You must give yourself up, Samson.
母亲  这是天主的旨意吗
Mother, is this what God wants?
我不确定
I'm not sure.
有时候
Sometimes,
天主在冥冥之中领导我们
God leads us in ways we cannot see.
天主会指引你的选择
God will guide your choices.
来
Come.
让开  退后
Stand aside! Stand back!
退后
Get back!
退开
Stay back!
你得到你的战利品了
You have your prize.
我看到的是一个凶手
All I see is a common murderer.
你也好不到哪去
No worse than you.
为什么要杀我的妻子
Why did you kill my wife?
为了给你和你的族人一个教训
To teach you and your people a lesson.
为拯救族人我愿牺牲自己
I gave myself up to save my people.
现在你愿意放了他们吗
Will you leave them alone now?
如果人手足够
If I had more men,
我会把你们通通赶回
I'd drive you all back
属于你们的荒芜之地
into the wilderness where you belong.
痛快地杀个片甲不留
I'd happily kill all of you.
杀了他
Kill him.
"你背负着赶走培肋舍特人的使命"
"Your duty is to drive the Philistines away."
"天主会指引你的选择"
"God will guide your choices."
我的上主天主  是你吗
My Lord God of Israel, is that you?
主啊  这是你希望我做的吗
Lord...is this what you want from me?
请指引我
Guide me, please.
过来
Come.
Come!
谢谢你
Thank you.
你叫什么名字
What is your name?
我叫德里拉
My name is Delilah.
达贡[培肋舍特人的主神]  天主  造物者
Dagon, God and Creator,
土地之神
Lord of our land,
请将三松
deliver into our hands,
我们的敌人  民族的破坏者
our enemy, Samson,
交予我们手中
destroyer of our nation.
有三松的消息了  他又找了个女人
We have news of Samson. He's got a new woman.
是个培肋舍特人
A Philistine woman.
又一个  她叫什么名字
Another one? What's her name?
德里拉
Delilah.
我认识她
I know her.
带她来见我
Bring her to me.
德里拉  感谢你能前来
Delilah... Thank you for coming.
-还是如此迷人  -你想怎么样
- As beguiling as ever. - What do you want?
让我们聊聊吧
Well, let's just have a little talk.
真是稀奇  你选择了三松
About Samson. An interesting choice.
一个外族男人
Not one of us, of course.
为什么要和他一起
Why are you with him?
为什么想知道
Why do you want to know?
别告诉我你关心他
Don't tell me you care about him.
-他爱上你了吗  -你自己去问他
- Is he in love with you? - Ask him yourself.
他屠杀了我们成百上千个的族人
He's butchered hundreds of our people.
他改变了
He's changed.
自从遇到我后  他已经改过自新
He's a different man since he's met me.
你真的相信吗
Do you really believe that?
他会继续杀戮
He will go on killing
直到我们找到办法除掉他
until we find a way to stop him for good.
他的力量从何而来  他的秘密是什么
Where does he get his strength? What's his secret?
我不知道
I don't know.
-他不会告诉我的  -试着说服他
- He won't tell me. - Try to convince him.
你难道没见识过他的能耐
Have you seen what he's capable of?
或许这个会有所帮助
Maybe this will help...
这是给你的危险报酬
Call it danger money.
全都是你的
It's all for you.
但不是现在
Uh-uh. Not now.
等到我们知道了他的秘密才是
Not until we know his secret.
你为何如此强壮
Why are you so strong?
天主与我同在  德里拉
God is with me, Delilah.
他赐我神力
He makes me strong.
"天主与你同在"是什么意思
What do you mean, 'God is with you'?
他如何赐你神力
How does he make you strong?
我母亲无法生育
My mother was barren.
天主给了她一个孩子
God brought her a child,
我
me.
但有些事情是我不能做的
But there are things I must not do.
比如说
Such as?
我从没剪过头发
I have never cut my hair.
这是禁忌
I am forbidden.
代表着我的忠诚
It's a sign of my devotion.
-倘若我剪了头发  我  -怎么样  亲爱的
- If I cut my hair, I... - What, my love?
倘若你剪了头发会怎么样
What if you cut your hair?
天主会收回我的神力
My god will take away all my strength.
我会变得同凡人一样羸弱
I'll be as weak as everyone else.
你不相信我吗
You don't believe me?
不  三松  我相信
No, Samson, I do.
三松
Samson!
抓住他
Take him!
怎么...
What...?
你做了什么
What have you done?
别自责
Don't feel bad.
每个人都有自己的价码
Everyone has their price.
德里拉
Delilah...
好好看看
Take a good look.
要记住你跟德里拉相遇的那天
And remember the day you first met the lovely Delilah.
你再也见不到她了
You will never see her again.
把他带走
Take him away.
我站不住了  让我靠着什么吧
I am weak. Stand me against something.
-主啊...  -安静
- Lord... - Quiet!
主啊...
Lord...
如果我是你选中的人  别放弃我
If I am yours, remember me now.
让我再次拥有力量
Strengthen me once more.
你的天主已经抛弃你了  三松
Your God has abandoned you, Samson.
是你使我双目失明的
You are the man who took away my eyes.
我很高兴
I am glad of it.
因为黑暗让我思考
For the darkness helps me think.
你的天主抛弃了你
Your God has deserted you
收回了你的神力
and taken your strength with him.
不...
No...
我现在能更清楚地感受到他
I can see him more clearly than ever.
他让我彻底毁了你们
He wants me to destroy you all!
结束了  三松
It's over, Samson!
阻止他  杀了他
Stop him! Kill him!
快
Now!
三松的牺牲也终结了数千培肋舍特人的性命
Samson's sacrifice kills thousands,
但他再也无法单枪匹马地反抗培肋舍特人了
but he could never defeat the Philistines on his own.
先知撒慕尔动员以色列人以天主之名团结一致
The Prophet Samuel has urged the people to unite in God's name.
天主至高无上
There is no one like the Lord.
但经过了数十年的努力
But after decades of struggle,
他还是没能阻止培肋舍特人的入侵
he too has failed to halt the Philistines.
先知  我们在等你
Prophet, we await you.
人们的耐心日渐丧失
And the people's patience is wearing thin.
你们在愁什么
So what is it that troubles you?
我们很感激你  先知
We are grateful, prophet.
你已领导我们多年
You have led us for many years...
是天主领导我们
God has led us!
撒慕尔...
Samuel...
你年龄渐长
You are not as young as you were.
我们很担心
We are worried.
在你之后  谁来和天主交流
Who will speak to the Lord after you?
谁会领导我们对抗培肋舍特人
Who will lead us against the Philistines?
我的儿子们会继承
My sons will inherit my place.
你的儿子们都腐败无能
Your sons are corrupt.
我的儿子们从小就信仰天主  谨遵他的教诲
My sons have been brought up to trust in God and obey his laws!
我为你们做的每件事
Everything I have done for you I have done
都是因为我行天主之道
because I walk in God's ways!
我们知道他们收受贿赂  人尽皆知
We know that they take bribes. Everyone knows it!
他们败坏了你的名声
They shame your good name.
当你不在
So, when you are gone,
培肋舍特人卷土重来  我们指望你的儿子们
and the Philistines return, and we look to your sons
呼求天主时...
to call on God...
天主会回应吗
will God answer?
不  不会
No, he will not.
那你们想怎么样
Then what do you want?
一位国王
A king.
就像其他国家一样
As other nations have.
但看看那些国家的国王都干了什么
But look what other nations' kings do.
他们变成暴君  奴役自己的子民
They become tyrants, they make slaves of their people.
由天主选中的国王不会这样
Not if they are chosen by God.
再由高尚的先知为其傅油选立
Anointed by his righteous prophet.
(傅油是一种宗教仪式 指被傅油的人是神所选定的)
就是您
By you.
你是要违抗天主吗
You would reject our God?
天主给予我们这片土地
God promised us this land.
这是天主的国度  他是唯一的国王
This is God's Kingdom. He is our only king.
你是天主之耳  撒慕尔
You have the ear of the Lord, Samuel.
(撒慕尔 意为"天主垂听了")
你必须请求他为我们选一位国王
You must ask him to choose a king for us.
你们都出去  所有人都出去
Leave me alone, all of you!
我曾奉献所有
I have given everything.
现在他们抛弃了我
Now they have rejected me.
和祢  天主
And you, God.
但如果你说我应该为他们找一位国王
But if you say I should give them a king,
我当然会这样做
then of course I will.
但谁能担此重任呢
But who should it be?
我知道了
I see...
那个人绝不可能是我
That could never be me.
但我仍是你的先知
But I will still be your prophet.
我会指引你的国王
I can guide your king.
撒乌尔
Saul.
愿你依照天主的法律
May you reign justly and wisely
进行客观公正的统治
according to God's law.
我傅你为以色列第一任国王
I anoint you the first king of Israel.
作为天主的先知  我将
May I, as God's prophet,
尽我所能地帮助你
help you in any way I can.
以色列史上的一个新时代开始了
A new era in Israelite history is beginning--
先知和国王的时代
The period of prophets and kings.
他们要共同保护盟约之地
They must work together to secure the promised land.
撒乌尔  撒乌尔
Saul! Saul!
《圣经》下集预告
Next time on The Bible
他们准备好了吗
Are the men ready?
准备好了
They are ready.
进攻前我们必须要进行祭祀
We must make a sacrifice before we attack.
愿天主宽恕你
May God forgive you.
担起国王的责任来
Be a king,
把祭祀的工作交给我
leave the job of priest to me.
你是我们的先知
You are our prophet,
但我是你的国王
but I am your king.
天主的恩赐随时可以收回
What the Lord gives, he can take away.
天主与我同在
God is with me!
主  你真的与他同在吗
Are you with him, Lord, really?
你违背了天主
You disobeyed the Lord.
他已经收回了你的王国
He has torn your kingdom from you
并将它赐予达味
and given it to David.
当你戴上我的王冠
When you have my crown,
你难道会不杀死我的后裔
will you not kill my descendants,
不消灭我的名
bury my name?
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem.
我们的新家园
Our new home.
国王永远不可能高于天主
A king is never above his God.
你滥用你的权利
You abused your power.
夺走了你最忠诚的仆人的一切
You took everything from your most loyal servant.
你夺人妻子
You took his wife,
然后又害死了他
then you took his life.
你以为天主对此一无所知吗
You think God doesn't see everything?
我是被他选中的人
I am his chosen one.
达味  他将给你民族带来大灾难
David, he will bring disaster on your house.
我们走着瞧
We shall see.
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!